Guide to the Winkler Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Winkler collection
1748-1854
YCGL MSS 14
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.26
(3 boxes)
The collection consists chiefly of letters to Winkler, Elisa von der Recke, and others. Also included are manuscripts of some original poems, a few printed works by and about Winkler, copies of documents pertaining to Winkler's family, including Festschriften in his honor, and photographic reproductions of portraits and drawings. Correspondents include H. C. (Hans Christian) Andersen, Sarah Austin, Ludwig Börne, Eduard Devrient, Johann Peter Eckermann, Paul Johann Anselm Ritter von Feuerbach, Christian Fürchtegott Gellert, Johann Wilhelm Ludewig Gleim, Ottilie von Goethe, Karl Gutzkow, E. T. A. Hoffman, August Wilhelm Iffland, Friedrich Maximilian Klinger, August von Kotzebue, Johann Caspar Lavater, Charles Joseph, prince de Ligne, Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Ludwig Tieck, Carl Maria von Weber.
Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Alfred E. Hamill, 1938.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
KARL GOTTFRIED THEODOR WINKLER (1775-1856)
Winkler, who used the pseudonym Theodor Hell, was born on 9 February 1775 near Dresden, the son of a clergyman. He studied law and history at Wittenberg and then returned to Dresden, where he held various positions and maintained a lifestyle rich in activities and connections. In 1796 he was appointed to the city court, and beginning in 1801 held positions of increasing responsibility with the city archive. When Saxony came under Russian control as a result of the Napoleonic wars, Winkler became a government secretary, edited government publications, and attained the rank of Russian privy councilor. By 1814 he was also active in the Dresden theater, rising eventually to vice-director of the court theater. His service to the German stage included his many translations of plays and operas, from French, English, Italian, and Portuguese, all languages in which he was well versed. He also wrote original prose and dramatic works, most of them now forgotten, and edited and published numerous periodicals, some of them influential. Among these publications were the literary annuals Penelope (1811-48) and Dramatisches Vergissmeinnicht (1824-49); the theater monthly Tagebuch der deutschen Bühnen (1815-35); and the newspaper the Dresden Abendzeitung, of which he was the editor from 1817-43. Winkler died in Dresden on 24 September 1856.
ELISA VON DER RECKE (1754-1833)
Born in Schönburg in the former Baltic province of Courland in 1756, the Komtesse Elisabeth von Medem was married as a teenager to the Baron von der Recke but divorced him several years later. She published poetry (Geistliche Lieder, 1780, Gedichte, 1806), autobiographical works, and travel writings, but was especially well known for her role in exposing the Italian adventurer Cagliostro, about whom she published a book in 1787. After her divorce, she travelled for many years, staying with friends, visiting spas, and taking part in court life in Berlin and Warsaw. From 1804 onward, the poet Christoph August Tiedge was her companion; in later years, they settled in Dresden, where the Countess Elisa died in 1833.
Scope and Contents
The Winkler Collection consists chiefly of letters to Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler, Elisa von der Recke, and others, 1748-1854. Also included are manuscripts of some original poems; a few printed works by and about Winkler; copies of documents pertaining to Winkler's family, including Festschriften in his honor, and photographs.
The Collection is organized into Correspondence,Writings, Printed Material and Photographs, and Martin Schütze's notes on Winkler. Correspondence is further organized into Letters to Winkler, Letters to Elisa von der Recke, Lavater-von der Recke, Lavater-Wieland, Letters to Heinrich Hase, Letters to George Friedrich Walther, and From and to Various Authors A-Z. Writings is further organized into Works and Letters by Winkler and Works, etc. by Various Authors.
Among the writers are Hans Christian Andersen, Sarah Austin, Ludwig Börne, David d'Angers, Eduard Devrient, Johann Peter Eckermann, Paul Johann Anselm Ritter von Feuerbach, Christian Fürchtegott Gellert, Johann Wilhelm Ludewig Gleim, Ottilie von Goethe, Karl Ferdinand Gutzkow, E. T. A. Hoffmann, August Wilhelm Iffland, Friedrich Maximilian Klinger, August Friedrich Ferdinand von Kotzebue, Johann Caspar Lavater, Charles Joseph, prince de Ligne, Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Ludwig Tieck, and Karl Maria von Weber. The Lavater - von der Recke correspondence was printed by Martin Schütze in Germanic Review, 1932, v. 7, p. 1-31, 201-214. There are transcriptions of all letters, and only a few of the many enclosures mentioned in the letters are present.
Authors, German -- 19th century; Andersen, H. C. (Hans Christian), 1805-1875; Austin, Sarah, 1793-1867; Börne, Ludwig, 1786-1837; Devrient, Eduard, 1801-1877; Eckermann, Johann Peter, 1792-1854; Feuerbach, Anselm, Ritter von, 1775-1833; Gellert, Christian Fürchtegott, 1715-1769; Gleim, Johann Wilhelm Ludewig, 1719-1803; Goethe, Ottilie von, 1796-1872; Gutzkow, Karl, 1811-1878; Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856; Hoffmann, E. T. A. (Ernst Theodor Amadeus), 1776-1822; Iffland, August Wilhelm, 1759-1814; Klinger, Friedrich Maximilian, 1752-1831; Kotzebue, August von, 1761-1819; Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801; Ligne, Charles Joseph, prince de, 1735-1814; Recke, Elisa von der, 1754-1833; Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Julius, 1794-1872; Schütze, Martin, 1866-1950; Tieck, Ludwig, 1773-1853; Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826
- Correspondence
  - LETTERS TO WINKLER
    - Ahlefeld, Charlotte (von Seebach) von, 1781-1849. ALS, Schleswig, 1818 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      1 p. Submitting a contribution for the Abendzeitung
    - Anderson, Hans Christian, 1805-1875. ALS, Berlin, 1844 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      1 p., with address Submitting his drama Der Mulatt in a German version by an unnamed translator
    - Angley, Louis, 1788-1835. ALS, Berlin, 1825 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      1 p., with address Concerning payment for Ziegler's Der weiblicher Husar and inquiring about submitting his own farce, Schüler- schwänke
    - Arvidsson, Adolf Iwar, 1791-1858. ALS, Stockholm, 1825 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      3 p. Librarian at the Royal Library Stockholm. Offering to send literary reports on Sweden, Finland and Russia
    - Atawinsky, Stanislaus. ALS, Breslau, 1826 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      1 p. Actor
    - Birch, Christian, 1794-1868. ALS, München, 1825 Apr 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      1 p. Submitting a note for the Abendzeitung correcting a statement concerning his wife Charlotte Birch-Pfeiffer, 1800- 1868
    - Blumenhagen, Wilhelm, 1781-1839. LS, Hannover, 1836 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      3 p. Giving advice and recommendation for Winkler's trip to England and promising a report for publication in the Vespertina
    - Blumroeder, August von, 1776-1860. ALS, Sonderhausen, 1818 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      3 p. Acknowledging Winkler's gift of the periodical Komus with some of his poems and sending him some contributions for the Komus
    - Boettiger, Karl August, 1760-1835. ALS (Box 1, Folder 9)
      1 p. Signed: B. "Boettiger" pencilled at foot of letter. Writer is unable to contribute theater reviews on account of serious eye trouble
    - Bonfigli, Antonio. ALS, Lucca, 1825 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      1 p. Opera singer at the Dresden theater. Begs to be excused; had to leave Italy where his father had died suddenly. In Italian
    - Brede, Auguste. ALS, Stuttgart, 1825 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      4 p. Actress and ballet dancer. She is embarking on a tournée of German theaters and asks Winkler to mention her plan in his newspaper
    - Breithaupt, Johann Friedrich August, 1791-1873. ALS, Freiberg, 1825 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      1 p. Mineralogist. Submitting contributions for the Abendzeitung
    - Bülow, Karl Eduard von, 1803-1853. ALS, Dresden, 1830 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      1 p. Editor of Friedrich Ulrich Ludwig Schröder's Dramatische Werke, 1834, 4 volumes. Concerns several of Schröder's works
    - Castelli, Ignaz Franz, 1781-1862. ALS, Wien, 1820 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chezy, Wilhelmine Christiane (von Klencke) von, 1786-1856. 4 ALS, 1818-25 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Concerning publication of her contributions in the Abendzeitung and the Vespertina; mention of her text to Karl Maria von Weber's opera Euryanthe
    - Cleever, J.H. ALS, Hannover, 1826 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      1 p. Submits announcement for printing in the Abendzeitung; mentions Weber's opera Oberon
    - Contessa, Karl Wilhelm Salice, 1777-1825. ALS, Sellendorf, 1817 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      3 p. Submitting the ms. of a farce and poem (not present) for publication in the Abendzeitung; refers to a contribution for the periodical Penelope
    - Duller, Eduard, 1809-1853. ALS, 1837 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      2 p. With mention of Winkler's article on Devrient and Iffland
    - Ebert, Friedrich Adolf, 1791-1834. ALS (Box 1, Folder 19)
      1 p. Librarian at Wolfenbüttel, 1823-25; chief librarian Dresden Library, 1827-1834. Concerning a rare copy of a work by Dibdin, owned by Brockhaus
    - Ellmenreich, Friederike (Brandl), 1775-1845. ALS, Frankfurt, 1826 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      4 p. Opera singer and translator of Italian and French opera texts. Offering seven of her texts
    - Feuerbach, Paul Johann Anslem Ritter von 1777-1883. ALS, München, 1808 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      2 p. At the time of writing Feuerbach was "Geheimer Referendar des bairischen Justizministeriums"; he was the author of the new codes on criminal and civil law
    - Förster, Karl August, 1784-1841. ALS, 1825 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      1 p. Professor of German language and literature at the military academy at Dresden
    - Franul von Weissenthurn, Johanna (Grünberg), 1773-1847. ALS, Wien, 1822 Oct 22 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      4 p. Playwright and actress
    - Franz, Agnes, 1794-1843. 2 ALS, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Gaal, Georg von, 1783-1855. ALS, Wien, 1826 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      3 p. Austrian poet, librarian for Prince von Esterhazy; director of the Vienna Art Gallery; compiler of a collection of proverbs in six languages
    - Genast, Eduard Franz, 1797-1866. ALS, Magdeburg, 1828 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      1 p. Actor and opera singer, chiefly at Weimar. Requesting the score of Oberon
    - Gensicke, Wilhelmine (Herz), 1779-1822. 3 ALS, 1817-20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      7 p. Writer of short stories
    - Griesinger, Georg August von, 1778-1845. 2 ALS, Wien, 1818-26 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      5 p. First letter with address Königlich Sächsischer Legationsrat at Wien
    - Grosse, Julie von. ALS, Breslau, 1839 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      1 p. Anticipating to find Mrs. Winkler at Bad Ischl on her arrival there; thanking for favorable reception given her short story and poems
    - Grüner, Karl Franz, 1780-1845. ALS, Darmstadt, 1818 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      1 p. His real name was Akács or von Akats. He was one of the actors for whom Goethe devised the Regeln für Schauspieler
    - Gutzkow, Karl Ferdinand, 1811-1878. ALS, Frankfurt, 1843 Nov 14 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Haake, August, 1793-1864. ALS, Breslau, 1836 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      1 p. On stationery of Direction des Breslauer Theaters. Actor and theater director. Requesting to forward an enclosed letter; enclosure not present
    - Haering, Wilhelm, 1798-1871. ALS, Berlin, 1825 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      1 p. Presenting a copy of the second edition of his novel Walladmor, which was attributed to Sir Walter Scott
    - Hagn, Charlotte von, 1809-1891. ALS, 1846 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      2 p. Actress, 1826-1833 at München, 1833-1846 at Berlin; she was married to Alexander von Owen from 1836-1851
    - Haizinger, Amalie (Morstadt), 1800-1884. ALS, Karlsruhe, 1826 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      1 p. Noted opera singer and actress, mainly at the Karlsruhe Hoftheater and the Vienna Burgtheater; was married (1816-1823) to Karl Neumann; married Anton Haizinger in 1827. Concerns her role in Winkler's Die Flitterwochen
    - Heeringen, Gustav Adolf von, 1800-1851. ALS, Coburg, 1835 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      3 p. Chiefly concerning his Fränkische Bilder, published 1835
    - Heinroth, Johann Christian August, 1773-1843. ALS, Leipzig, 1817 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      2 p. Noted physician and professor of medicine; author of works on psychiatry and of the belletristic Gesammelte Blätter which in this letter he submits to Winkler for the Abendzeitung
    - Heun, Karl Gottlieb Samuel, 1771-1854. ALS (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Hoffmann, Ernest Theodor Amadeus, 1776-1822. 2 ALS, Dresden, 1813 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      On his arrival at Dresden he found Joseph Seconda not yet present; asks for an advance so he may pay the driver and some necessary purchases
    - Holbein, Franz Ignaz von, Elder von Holbeinsberg, 1779-1855. 8 ALS, 1831-36 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      22 p. Actor, dramatist, director at various theaters, chiefly in Prague, Hannover and Weimar
    - Horn, Franz Christoph, 1781-1837. ALS, Berlin, 1825 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      4 p. Concerning his lectures on Shakespeare; forwarding unnamed works and submitting an article for the Abendzeitung
    - Hülle, Hedwig (Hoffmeier), 1794-1861. ALS, Breman, 1821 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      3 p. Asking support in her intention to have her collected works published by subscription. Enclosure: clipping from Bremer Zeitung with her announcement; the copy of a poem, which was also enclosed, is not present
    - Houwald, Ernest Christoph Freiherr von, 1778-1845. 3 ALS, 1818-22 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      10 p. Concerning his plays Heimkehr and Seinem Schicksal kann niemand entgehen and contributions for the periodicals Penelope and Komus
    - Jutranisch, Wilhelm Baron von. ALS, Wien, 1818 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      1 p. Forwarding two böhmische Kinder, poems; he is still holding the oesterreichische in abeyance
    - Kalckreuth, Friedrich Graf von, 1790-1873. ALS, Villa Grassi, 1825 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      3 p. Concerning an obituary for Otto Graf von Loeben
    - Karl Alexander, Grand Duke of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, 1818-1901. ALS, Weimar, 1844 Aug 17 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      1 p. Thanking for a congratulatory poem by Winkler sent for the occasion of the birth of Prince Karl August on July 31, 1844
    - Kind, Johann Friedrich, 1768-1843. 2 ALS, 1822 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Author; joint editor 1817-1826 with KGTW, of the Abendzeitung. Author of the text of the opera Der Freischütz, by Carl Maria von Weber. The first letter concerns Kind's text for Freischütz; the second, contributions by Winkler and Kind to the various periodicals with which both were connected
    - Klingemann, August, 1777-1831. ALS, Braunschweig, 1825 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      3 p. Dramatist and theater director, chiefly at Braunschweig, where on January 29, 1829, he produced Goethe's Faust for the first time. The letter relates to the production of his Ahasver
    - Köchy, Karl Georg Heinrich Eduard, 1800-1880. ALS, Braunschweig, 1826 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      1 p. Theater director and writer. Submitting an article in the form of a dialogue on the subject Improvisation for the Taschenbuch or the Abendzeitung and promising a short story for the Penelope
    - König, Fr. ALS, Stuttgart, 1818 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      1 p. Submitting some contribution for the Abendzeitung
    - Körner, Julius, 1793-1873. ALS, Schneeberg, 1818 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      2 p. Sending two scenes of a tragedy (probably his Niobe, published 1821) for publication
    - Kotzebue, August Friedrich Ferdinand von 1761-1819. ALS, Mannheim, 1818 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      4 p.
    - Krug von Nidda, Friedrich Albert Franz, 1776-1843. ALS, Querfurth, 1826 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      1 p. Offering a Romanze for printing in the Penelope.
    - Küstner, Karl Theodor von, 1784-1864. 2 AlS, Leipzig, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      2 p. Theater director, founder of Leipzig Stadttheater
    - Leonhardt, M. ALS, 1825 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      1 p. On stationery with a watermark representing Friedrich August I, King of Saxony. Concerning the baptism of Winkler's daughter.
    - Lessing, Karoline (Meitzen), 1779-1834. ALS, Schweidnitz, 1824 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      1 p. Author of short stories, plays and poems. Concerning various contributions to the Abendzeitung and her new historical novel on Maximilian II; mentions the birth of Winkler's daughter
    - Lindenau, Bernhard August von 1779-1854. ALS, Altenburg, 1847 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      1 p. Astronomer, prominent Saxon statesman, director of the collections of the arts and sciences in Dresden
    - Lützow, Therese (von Struve) von, 1804-1852. 2 ALS, Hamburg, 1841-47 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      6 p. In the first letter the writer inquires about the possibility of having articles by her published in the Abendzeitung; the second acknowledges the visit from Winkler's son-in-law
    - Mahlmann, August, 1771-1826. ALS, Leipzig, 1816 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      1 p. Editor, 1805-10 alone, 1810-16 with Methusalem Müller, of the Zeitung für die elegante Welt; 1810-1818 of the Leipziger Zeitung
    - Malsburg, Ernst Freiherr von der, 1786-1824. ALS, Dresden, 1820 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      1 p. Submitting an article for the Vespertina and promising better ones for the Abendzeitung
    - Manteuffel. ALS, Tharandt, 1817 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      4 p. Offering a number of his writings for possible publication in the Abendzeitung
    - Marr, Heinrich, 1797-1871. ALS, Braunschweig, 1826 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      2 p. Actor and stage manager. Second leaf mutilated with slight loss of text
    - Marsano, Wilhelm von, 1797-1871. ALS, Prague, 1828 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      1 p. Austrian "Feldmarschallieutenant" and writer. Thanking Winkler for mentioning his Romantische Dichtungen in the Abendzeitung and expressing he will do the same for Spessart.
    - Marschner, Heinrich August, 1795-1861. ALS, Hannover, 1846 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      1 p. Composer, chiefly of operas; music director at the Dresden theater, 1824-1825, from 1830-1859 at Hannover. Referring Winkler to his brother- in-law Wilhelm August Wohlbrück as the owner of the posthumous papers of the actor Johann Gottfried Wohlbrück
    - Mayer, Sophie Friederike Elise, 1788-1827. ALS, Berlin, 1822 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      1 p. The author wrote under the pseudonym Sophie May. Submitting her work Thalia for publication
    - Meyer, Hans Heinrich, 1760-1832. ALS, Weimar, 1823 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      2 p. Goethe's friend, painter and art historian. Refers to his version of a manuscript of the index to an unnamed publication; promises to resume his work on certain copper-plates
    - Mittell, Peter, 1769-1824. ALS, Karlsruhe, 1821 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      1 p. Member and at times producer at the Karlsruhe Hoftheater. Among the plays requested from KGTW is Torquato Tasso
    - Morlacchi, Francesco, 1784-1841. 2 ALS, Marienbad; Töplitz, 1825-26 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      3 p. Composer of church music and operas; 1810-1841, conductor of opera at the Dresden theater. In Italian
    - Mühling, Julius, 1793-1874. LS, Hamburg, 1843 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      1 p. Signed: Mühling and J. Cornet Both were opera singers, actors and theater directors from 1841- 1847 both jointly in Hamburg. Acknowledging the receipt of the comedy Der Sohn Cromwells
    - Müller, Karl Ludwig Methusalem, 1771-1837. ALS, Leipzig, 1825 Aug 24 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      1 p. Asking to forward a letter to Herrn Weissflog; enclosure not present
    - Müller, Sophie, 1803-1830. ALS, Wien, 1826 Sep 30 (Box 1, Folder 71)
      2 p. Actress chiefly at the Vienna Burgtheater. Permission to have her portrait published in Winkler's almanac; reports the enthusiastic reception of his play Die erste Liebschaft
    - Müller, Wilhelm, 1794-1827. ALS, Dessau, 1825 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 72)
      2 p. Introducing the violinist and composer Lindner
    - Müllner, Adolf, 1774-1829. ALS, Weissenfels, 1818 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      1 p. Concerns a laudatory poem
    - Neumann, Johanna (Hiepe), 1787-1863. ALS (Box 1, Folder 74)
      4 p. Novelist and author of children's books; founder and principal of a boarding school for girls. Congratulations at the birth of Winkler's child; discusses some of her works
    - Oefele, Aloys Freiherr von. ALS, Regenburg, 1826 Apr 1 (Box 1, Folder 75)
      3 p. Offering a fragment, part of 18 chapters in 3 volumes, of the Russian novel Olga, in the style of Sir Walter Scott
    - Pellet, Josef. ALS, Gratz, 1837 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 76)
      1 p. Requesting copies of Vetter Heinrich and of Pflegevater
    - Peters, Adolf, 1830-1876. ALS, Leipzig, 1826 Jan 18 (Box 1, Folder 77)
      2 p. Mathematician and writer of poetry. Forwarding a group of poems for publication in the Abendzeitung and also a short story written by an unnamed friend
    - Prätzel, Karl Gottlieb, 1785-1861. ALS, Hamburg, 1825 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 78)
      1 p. Introducing Königl. Preuss. Oberpostcommissair Rüppell who is coming on a visit to Dresden; promising further contributions to Abendzeitung
    - Quandt, Johann Gottlob von, 1787-1859. ALS, Leipzig, 1816 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 79)
      4 p. Art historian and collector; associate of Goethe
    - Reichenbach, Heinrich Gottlob Ludwig, 1793-1879. ALS, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 80)
      4 p. Botanist and zoologist. Concerns a review of a work by Oken; good wishes and suggestions for Winkler's trip to the Netherlands, including introductions to some of his friends there
    - Reinhardt, Friederike (Wagner), 1770-1843. ALS, Oberndorf bei Arnstadt, 1821 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      1 p. Offering a work for publication
    - Reinhold, Karl Wilhelm, 1777-1841. ALS, Hamburg, 1821 Aug 6 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      1 p. Originally named Zacharias Lehmann. Journalist and writer for the theater; editor of various periodicals
    - Remie, Clemens. ALS, Maynz, 1826 Nov 9 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      3 p. Theater director
    - Ringelhardt. ALS, Leipzig, 1836 Oct 1 (Box 2, Folder 84)
      1 p.
    - Rousseau, Johann Baptist, 1802-1867. ALS, Aachen, 1825 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 85)
      1 p. A poet and editor of several journals. Sending a copy of his tragedy Michelangelo for announcement in the Abendzeitung; offering to report on Aachen in return for some contributions by Winkler for the Rheinische Flora
    - Saphir, Moriz Gottlieb, 1795-1858. ALS, Berlin, 1825 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      1 p. Submitting two poems for printing in the Abendzeitung and offering reports from his tour through Germany, Netherlands, France and England beginning with Breslau and Berlin. Printed announcement (dated September 1825) of a new periodical (probably Berliner Schnellpost für Litteratur, Theater und Geselligkeit) asking to have it inserted in the Abendzeitung. With a handwritten request for contributions from Winkler's pen.
    - Schall, Karl, 1780-1833. 2 ALS, Breslau, 1817-25 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Schmidt, Friedrich Ludwig, 1772-1841. ALS, Hamburg, 1825 Apr 8 (Box 2, Folder 88)
      1 p. Dramatist and theater director, chiefly at Hamburg. Letter mutilated at the top with partial loss of place of origin
    - Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Veit Hans, 1764-1841. ALS, Leipzig, 1825 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      2 p. Artist chiefly of book illustrations; of the gallery of fine arts at Leipzig
    - Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Julius, 1794-1872. ALS, Dresden, 1854 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 90)